Guide to the Edward J. Falkowski Papers TAM.120
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Edward J. Falkowski Papers
Bulk, 1930-1970
1910-1983
TAM.120
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
13.25 linear feet in 9 record cartons, 12 custom-made boxes for scrapbooks, and 5 folders
Edward J. Falkowski (1901-1984) was a journalist, trade unionist, and radical who was politically close to the communist movement in the 1920s-1940s. He was a prolific writer, contributing articles to left-wing journals throughout his life. He spent the years 1930-1937 living in the Soviet Union and writing for the English-language paper Moscow News. In addition to being a journalist, in the 1950s Falkowski was also a shop steward to the United Automobile, Aircraft and Agricultural Implement Workers of America (UAW), Local 365. The collection documents Falkowski's years in the Soviet Union, his involvement with Local 365, the evolution of his work as a writer and journalist, and his family relationships. The collection mainly consists of Falkowski's published and unpublished writings, correspondence, journals, scrapbooks, and labor union records.
Falkowski, Edward J., 1901-1984
Historical/Biographical Note
Edward J. Falkowski (1901-1984) was a journalist, trade unionist, and radical who was politically close to the communist movement in the 1920s-1940s. He was born in Shenandoah, Pennsylvania in 1901. As a teenager, Falkowski began working in the coal mines, and he became active in the United Mine Workers (UMW). In 1926, Falkowski began attending Brookwood Labor College in Katonah, New York on a UMW scholarship. During this time, Falkowski's articles and poetry first appeared in Labor Age and New Masses. (Falkowski used two pseudonyms in his published writings: "Edward Fulsky" in the 1920s and "Polonicus" in the 1970s.)
In 1928, Falkowski traveled to Germany as a work exchange student. Encouraged by friends and attracted politically to the Russian Revolution, he decided to visit and write about the Soviet Union, arriving in May 1930. He remained in the Soviet Union for seven years, during which time he worked as a journalist for the Moscow News (an English-language paper), married, and began raising a family. In 1937, he left the Soviet Union and returned to the United States, where he settled in Toledo, Ohio. He taught for a time at Commonwealth College in Mena, Arkansas, then was drafted into the army. After his service, he remarried and continued his writing activities.
In the mid 1940s, at the urging of labor organizer Leo Krzycki, Falkowski helped organize and worked for the communist-associated American Slav Congress, an umbrella organization of Slavic Americans. He later directed a Polish press agency.
As a factory worker in the plastics department at Eagle Electric Manufacturing Company in the 1950s, Falkowski served as shop steward to the United Automobile, Aircraft and Agricultural Implement Workers of America (UAW), Local 365 in Queens, New York. He moved into a management position at Eagle Electric in 1959.
In the 1960s, Falkowski was active in New York City housing issues, worked as a field interviewer for the National Opinion Research Center, and contributed articles to the Christian Herald, Good Business, Supervision, Modern Management, Christian Science Sentinal, New Republic, and New Freeman.
Falkowski died in New York City in 1984.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials in the collection are extremely brittle. Please use care when handling materials.
Related Archival Materials
There is also a collection of Edward Falkowski's papers at the Walter P. Reuther Library at Wayne State University.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series. Folders are arranged alphabetically or chronologically within each series.
Series I: Journals
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Writings
Series IV: Scrapbooks and Photographs
Series V: UAW, Local 365
Series VI: Moscow Years
Series VII: Unprocessed Materials
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Helen Falkowski, widow of Edward J. Falkowski, sent a gift of Edward Falkowski's papers in 1984. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1984.019, 1984.02 and NPA.2005.056.
Scope and Contents note
The collection spans over eight decades and documents Falkowski's years in the Soviet Union; his involvement with UAW, Local 365 and his employment at Eagle Electric; the evolution of his work as a writer and journalist; and his family relationships. The collection consists of Falkowski's published and unpublished writings, correspondence, journals, and scrapbooks. It also contains photographs, notes, biographical materials, and labor union records.
Separated Materials
A run of the Polish Press Agency from 1944 to 1946, featuring articles written by Falkowski, was separated for library cataloging.
Adamic, Louis, 1899-1951; American Slav Congress.; Conroy, Jack, 1898-1990; Eagle Electronics (Firm).; Falkowski, Edward J., 1901-1984; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; North, Joseph; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America.; Articles.; Communists |z United States.; Correspondence.; Germany |x Description and travel.; Journalism, Communist.; Labor journalism |z United States.; Manuscripts (document genre); Photographs.; Polish Americans |v Biography.; Socialists |z United States.; Soviet Union |x Description and travel.
- Series I: Journals, 1917-1982
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I contains the journals Falkowski maintained throughout his life. The journals are particularly valuable for their documentation of his early years and his time in Germany and the Soviet Union.
  - Journals, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Journals, 1920s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Journals, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Journals, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Journals, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Journals, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Journals, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7A-7B)
  - Journals, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8A-8B)
  - Journals, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Journals, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Journals, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 11A-11B)
  - Journals, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Journals, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 13A-13B)
  - Journals, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 14A-14B)
  - Journals, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Journals, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 16A-16B)
  - Journals, 195_? (1950s) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Journals, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 18A-18B)
  - Journals, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Journals, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Journals, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Journals, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Journals, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Journals, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Journals, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Journals, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Journals, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Journals, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8A-8B, 9A-9B)
  - Journals, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 10A-10B)
  - Journals, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Journals, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Journals, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Journals, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1910-1983
  Series II is primarily Falkowski's correspondence with his family, especially his wife and siblings. Prominent correspondents include Joseph North, Jack Conroy, Louis Adamic, and Elizabeth Gurely Flynn.
  - Correspondence, 1910s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1920s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Hannah (?), December 1928-April 1934 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Clyde Beasley, March 1979-August 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jon Bloom, September 1976-February 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Inga Christensen, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Jack Conroy, October 1937-August 1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Viola Cooper, July 1940-May 1942 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Harold Dellinger, December 1975-December 1978 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Harold Dellinger, January 1979-August 1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Edna Falkowski Nofen, July 1938-June 1982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - George Falkowski, July 1968-December 1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - George Falkowski, January 1977-January 1983, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Helen Falkowski, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Helena Falkowski, June 1922-November 1964 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - John Falkowski, August 1978-June 1982 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Paul Falkowski, June 1961-May 1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Stanley Falkowski, January 1927-August 1951 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Walter Falkowski, July 1917-1930s (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Boleslaw Gebert, February 1969-February 1979 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - John Maliniak, May 1976-June 1982 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Polish Embassy, 1945-1968 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Rose Prokofiev, October 1931-December 1937 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Rose Prokofiev, February 1938-September 1945 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Rose Prokofiev, December 1973-May 1980 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - William Seligman, March 1974-August 1982 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Tracy Strong, October 1980-October 1981 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Juan Tomaszewski, November 1971-October 1978 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Juan Tomaszewski, June 1979-June 1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Ann Utterback, December 1976-March 1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Wayne State University, February 1974-June 1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Douglas Wixson, February 1982-August 1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Undated and Fragments (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series III: Writings, 1910-1970s
  Series III contains both published and unpublished works by Falkowski.
  - Subseries A: Published Writings
    Journals for which Falkowski wrote include Labor Age, New Masses, Rebel Poet, The Anvil, Moscow News, Polish American Journal, and People's Voice (under the pen name "Polonicus"). He also wrote for the Federated Press, a leftist labor news service.
    - The Anvil thru Fur den Sonntag, 1930s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Good Business thru New Freeman, 1920s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - New Masses, 1920s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - People's Voice, 1950s-1970s (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Observer thru Young Outlook, 1930s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Unknown Sources, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Subseries B: Literary Manuscripts
    The literary manuscripts consist of Falkowski's poetry, sketches, short stories, plays, and novels. The first folder in the subseries contains four unique issues of a literary journal produced by Falkowski and his friends in Pennsylvania.
    - Chapbooks, 1920s (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Notes on Art, Books, etc., 1960s-1970s, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Notecards, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Novel: Anthracite, undated (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - Novel: Dawn Lantern, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Novel: Iron Vineyard, undated (Box 5, Folder 7-12)
    - Plays, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Play: Dark Circle, undated (Box 4, Folder 15-17)
    - Plays: Untitled and Fragments, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Poems, 1960s-1970s, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Poems and Prose, 1910-1930 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Stories, undated (Box 4, Folder 20-27)
    - Stories: Untitled and Fragments, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Subseries C: Journalism, Notes, Interviews, Biography, and Autobiography
    The subseries includes interviews and manuscripts produced from Falkowski's work as a journalist. It also includes Falkowski's autobiography and other biographical materials.
    - Biography, Autobiography, ID Cards, and Miscellaneous Biographical Materials, 1940s-1970s, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Journalism and Notes: Arkansas, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Journalism and Notes: Coal, 1941, undated (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
    - Journalism and Notes: College at Sixty, 1949, 1977, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Journalism and Notes: Germany, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Journalism and Notes: Grant House, 1960s, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Journalism and Notes: Ohio, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Journalism and Notes: Polish Matters, 1960s-1970s, undated (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
    - Journalism and Notes: "Polonicus", 1960s, undated (Box 6, Folder 11-13)
    - Journalism and Notes: Soviet Union, undated (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Journalism and Notes: Work, 1950s, undated (Box 6, Folder 14-16)
    - Interviews: Jeff Davis, 1940s, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Interviews: National Opinion Research Center (N.O.R.C.), 1960s, undated (Box 6, Folder 20-21)
    - Interviews: National Opinion Research Center (N.O.R.C.), 1960s, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks and Photographs
  Series IV contains twenty-seven scrapbooks, given sixteen subject titles by Falkowski. The major subject areas are mine workers and the UMW, Polish Americans, and Americans in the USSR. There are also a small number of photographs, postcards, and other graphic materials, primarily regarding coal mining in Pennsylvania and the American Slav Congress.
  - Scrapbook: Falkowski Writings, circa 1930-1970 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbooks: Fight to Save the Mines and Union Issues and Politics, circa 1930-1970 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks: Memoribilia, Moscow News: USSR Spetzes, Metro Spetzes Industry, circa 1930-1970 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbooks: Moscow News: Americans in USSR, Moscow News: Coal, Moscow News: Americans in USSR, circa 1930-1970 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks: Moscow News: Americans in USSR, Moscow News: USSR Culture, Moscow News: USSR Culture and Literature, circa 1930-1970 (Box 14)
  - Scrapbooks: Pennsylvnia Coal Mining, Coal Mining in the USA, Moscow News: Coal Special Features, circa 1930-1970 (Box 15)
  - Scrapbooks: Polish Clippings, Polonicus Clippins, Post-War Problems in Poland, circa 1930-1970 (Box 16)
  - Scrapbooks: Polish Emigres, Wartime Struggles of Emigre Groups, circa 1930-1970 (Box 17)
  - Scrapbook: Polish Emigres During the War, circa 1930-1970 (Box 18)
  - Scrapbooks: Post-War Lithuania and Baltic States, Moscow News: Clippings, Toledo Clippings, circa 1930-1970 (Box 19)
  - Scrapbook: Slav Congress in Poland, circa 1930-1970 (Box 20)
  - Scrapbooks: War Years in Poland, Moscow News: USSR Culture and Literature, circa 1930-1970 (Box 21)
  - Coal Mining, undated (Box OS 001)
  - Coal Mining, 1889, 1918, undated (Box A 002, Folder 1)
  - Portraits and Signed Photographs, 1970s, undated (Box A 002, Folder 2)
  - Sketch (Falkowski?), undated (Box A 002, Folder 3)
  - Slav Congress, 1938, 1941, 1945 (Box A 002, Folder 4)
- Series V: United Automobile, Aircraft and Agricultural Implement Workers of America (UAW), Local 365
  Series V documents Falkowski's involvement with UAW, Local 365 during his employment in the plastics department at Eagle Electric Manufacturing Company in the 1950s. The series mostly consists of contract negotiations between Local 365 and Eagle Electric, Falkowski's shop notes, correspondence between Local 365 and Eagle Electric, and Eagle Electric inter-office correspondence.
  - Benefits, 1950s, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Constitutions, 1950s, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1950-1953 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1954-1956 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Contract Negotiations, 1957-1959 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Contract Negotiations, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Dues Book, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Eagle Plastics Products and Equipment, 1950s, undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Elections, 1950s, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Falkowski Correspondence, 1954, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Grievances and Arbitrations, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Membership, 1950s, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Minutes, 1950s-1960 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters and Notices, 1950s, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Shop Correspondence, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Shop Notes, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Shop Notes, 1951-1954 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Shop Notes, 1955-1958 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Shop Notes, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Shop Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Shop Steward Manual, circa 1956 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Shop Stories, undated (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
- Series VI: Moscow Years
  Series VI documents Falkowski's years in the Soviet Union. The materials in this series provide a first-hand account, through Falkowski's personal observations and interviews, of the daily life of industrial and agricultural workers in the 1930s. The materials offer insight into the workers' perceptions of the period's economic and political transformation, as well as their reactions from social and cultural viewpoints. There are also draft notes and essays on foreign specialists that document their perceptions of the Soviet Union and the conditions under which they worked and lived.
  The series includes two unpublished manuscripts for novels that take place in the Soviet Union, one titled "Boris" and one which is untitled.
  To a lesser extent, the series contains subject files on topics such as courts and trials, housing, press and journalism, and theatrical and fine arts. There are also a small number of profiles and interviews regarding literature and literary figures.
  - Agriculture, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - "Boris" Synopsis and Fragmented Manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Coal Mines, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, May 28, 1930-July 25, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Courts and Trials, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Foreign Specialists, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Fragmented Journal Entries, January 6-December 30 [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Fragmented Journal Entries, undated [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - General Fragmented Writings, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Housing, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Industry, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Interviews and Profiles of Literaries, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Journal Entries, May 13, 1930-May 11, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Journal Entries, January 3-March 31 [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Journal Entries, April 3-June 28 [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Journal Entries, July 2-September 30 [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Journal Entries, October 3-December 30 [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - "Lenin's Literary Style" (by Falkowski), undated (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Press and Journalism, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Published Articles on Soviet Literature, 1932, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Series of Published Articles on Coal Mining Operations, 1930-1933 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Soviet Writers on Literary Topics, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Theatrical and Fine Arts, [1930-1937] (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Untitled Book Manuscript (Two Drafts), undated (Box 10, Folder 26)
- Series VII: Unprocessed Materials
  Series VII contains unprocessed materials and duplicates.
  - Unprocessed Materials and Duplicates, undated (Box 11)